Today we're talking about Tessa Morlin
which is a growth hormone secret and
this video is at the request of my
friend and colleague Dr. Steven Dvos of
the TRT and hormone optimization YouTube
channel. So Tessa Morlin works as an
endogenous analog of what's known as
growth hormone releasing hormone. And
GHR is released from the hypothalamus
and then GHRH tells the anterior
pituitary to make growth hormone. and
when growth hormones released. It has a
downstream stimulation on the production
of IGF-1 from the liver. So tesamor was
released I believe in 2009 2010 under
the FDA approved name called erya and it
was indicated for patients who have HIV
lipodistrophe. HIV lipodistrophe is a
condition where you have a
redistribution of your fat or you should
say a change in your body composition.
So you have a reduction in subcutaneous
fat but you have an increase in visceral
fat particularly central visceral
atyposity. So all around the torso. So
you have a reduction of fat in the
limbs. So arms, legs, also an increase
of fat on the torso cervical region
which is back here by the shoulder
blades. And we sometimes refer to that
as the buffalo hump. And some of the
consequences of HIV lipodistrophe are
increased central atypoposity which can
lead to fatty liver disease, insulin
resistance, metabolic disgraas such as
increased triglycerides, worsening lipid
profile as well as increased
cardiovascular risk. And HIV
lipodistrophe can be a result of the
anti-retroviral drugs such as the
protease inhibitors. even if they're not
on the drugs, some patients with HIV can
still experience lipodistrophe, but it
is more highly correlated with the
administration and utilization of the
HIV anti-retrovirals. So, some
treatments of HIV lipodistrophe include
things such as metformin or drugs
belonging to a class of drugs such as
the TZDs. So, a drug like that would be
paglitazone. Some people elect for
plastic surgery and the last one which
brings us here which is Tessa Morlin.
And the reason tessamorin has been
implicated and utilized as a tool in
treating lipodistrophe is because we
know that growth hormone is great at
breaking down fat tissue. It does so
through a process called lipolysis and
there's several proposed mechanisms of
action of how it does this and hormone
sensitive lipase is one of the pathways.
atapose triglyceride lipase is another
pathway it does this as well as other
mechanisms of action that we don't fully
know in some of the HIV lipodistrov
trials it was shown that tessaorin can
help reduce VAT which is visceral
atapost tissue upwards of 15% in the
intervention group whereas the group who
received placebo practically had no
change whatsoever it was less than 1% as
to be expected now the results for the
testimor treated group yes it did
sustain ain those results as long as
they were remaining on the drug. Besides
reductions in visceral fat, the patients
treated also demonstrated improvements
in liver fat. So fatty liver disease,
which has now been renamed MASH, M A SH,
which means metabolic associated
dysfunction, stato hepatitis, because it
encompasses a constellation of different
things that's going on. Besides
improving MASH and/or what we call fatty
liver disease, it's also been shown to
reduce triglycerides. In the studies, it
shown about a 50 pointish reduction. And
cholesterol levels, it also showed about
a 30% reduction as well. Now, in the
lipodistrophe groups though, once they
discontinue the drug, it's possible that
they could reaccumulate some of that
fat. Can we extrapolate these same
results to the general population who
does not have lipodistrophe, who does
not have HIV, who are not on
anti-retroviral drugs, that I don't
know. And lastly, it's demonstrated
ongoing and static improvements in IGF-1
production from the liver, which is to
be expected. Now, I have gripes about
IGF-1 testing, which include the fact
that IGF-1 isn't the most specific for
GH production because there's other
factors at play. I mean, you could have
GH resistance, liver disease, thyroid
disease, estradile production. There's
multiple things going into play when it
comes to IGF-1 production. But I
digress. So, not only can Tesmorlin
improve you cosmetically, it can also
improve you metabolically. Next, let's
talk about safety concerns of tessamlin.
The biggest safety concern would be
malignancy, which if you have a
malignancy that you know about, you
shouldn't take this drug period. But
then again, if you have a malignancy,
chances are you're probably not that
worried about reducing visceral fat.
Glucose intolerance, which an increase
in your blood sugar could theoretically
occur with this drug. If you're an
otherwise healthy person, i.e. someone
who doesn't have a metabolic dysfunction
such as insulin resistance, MASH,
obesity, something like that, I probably
wouldn't be overtly concerned about
glucose intolerance. Now, let's say you
are someone who does have lipodistrophe.
That in of itself puts you in a maloo
that predisposes you to having high
blood sugar and then you add a drug that
could theoretically possibly increase
that. And that's why you could possibly
see a concern there. A little bit of
fluid retention is pretty darn common.
Some people complain about arthralgas,
which is some joint ache, joint pain,
and IGF mediated drugs are somewhat
known for doing that. And icaria, which
occurs in about 3 to 5% of people, and
that's just itchy rash and flushing.
Otherwise, it's a pretty well tolerated
drug to be quite honest with you.
Personally, what I've seen the most
clinically and anecdotally is flushing
and itchiness at the injection site. And
lastly, what I've seen again clinically
and in practice is that Tessa Morlin
goes great with TRT and with the GLP1.
That triple stack has a very compounding
effect on a patient's composition and
overall metabolic health. As long as the
patient is tolerating the drugs well,
putting in the work, eating right,
training hard like they should be, I see
that combination work incredibly well.
Shout out to Steve for wanting me to
touch base on this drug and dig a little
deeper into it. If you have any
questions, leave in the comments. Give
me a shout and we can talk more. Thanks.
Hey,
hey,
hey.